Guide to the Shirley Hayes Papers 1948-2001 (Bulk 1952-1979) MS 292
New-York Historical Society
Shirley Hayes papers
1948-2001 (bulk 1952-1979)
New-York Historical Society
Hayes, Shirley, 1921-2001
MS 292
16.75 Linear feet in 27 boxes.
Shirley Hayes was a long-time resident of the Washington Square Park area. While she lived there she was active in many local community groups. This collection contains information on the activities she was involved in, her political involvement, and her job at WNYC.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Chris and Kerry Hayes, 2002 (accession no. MS-2002-09).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in fifteen series:
Series I.
Washington Square Park Battle, 1952-1959
Series II.
Washington Square Park Renovation Effort, 1958-1969
Series III.
Greenwich Village Battles, 1960-1993
Series IV.
Greenwich Village/Washington Square Park Histories, 1988
Series V.
Community Planning Board #2, 1952-1993
Series VI.
City Publications, 1952-1993
Series VII.
Political Campaigns, 1952-1969
Series VIII.
WNYC, American Federation of Television and Radio Arts (AFTRA) and Related Materials, 1960-1978
Series IX.
Other Organizations, Events, Activities and Issues of Interest to Shirley Hayes, 1951-1976
Series X.
Personal Items, 1948-2001
Series XI.
Articles and Clippings, 1952-1980
Series XII.
Visual Materials, 1952-1993
Series XIII.
Recordings, Undated
Series XIV.
Notes, Drafts, and Fragments, 1953-1967
Series XV.
Duplicate and unsorted material, circa 1952-1961
Biographical Note
Shirley Zak Hayes was born on June 15, 1912 in Chicago. She attended the University of Wisconsin and studied painting at the Art Institute of Chicago and studied at the Goodman Theatre of School of Drama. In 1932 she moved to New York to pursue her career as an actress. While in the show "Hamlet", she met her husband James. Together they had four sons. Hayes and James divorced in 1965.
Shirley Hayes was a community activist most of her life. The main focus of this activism was on the Greenwich Village and Washington Square Park areas. The movement she is most known for is the fight to close Washington Square Park to traffic. In 1959, she finally succeeded. Some of the other causes she fought for were contesting large apartment buildings on the square, fighting the New York University Bobst Library, and getting more playgrounds in the area. She was also instrumental in renovating the park after it was closed to traffic. The Washington Square Park Committee was formed to help conserve the park, and Hayes was Chairman of the committee for many years. Other community organizations she was on were the Greenwich Village Association and the Community Planning Board #2.
She was also involved in local politics. She worked on John Lindsay's re-election to Congress in 1964, his mayoral election in 1965 and mayoral re-election in 1969. During this time she also worked at WNYC, the city run radio station. She was the first woman announcer at WNYC. While at WNYC she became active in the American Federation of Television and Film Arts.
In 2001, the Parks Department of New York City honored Hayes with a plaque in Washington Square Park. The plaque tells of her fight to close the park to traffic. Hayes passed away on May 6, 2002.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Further material on Washington Square Park can be found in the Washington Arch Records, 1872-1925 (MS 443.30) and in the Washington Square Park Redevelopment Collection, 1952-1966 (MS 678). See also the Shirley Hayes collection, 1952-1974 (MS 2958.4434).
Scope and Content Note
The Shirley Hayes Papers (1948-2001) primarily documents the Greenwich Village activism of Shirley Zak Hayes who successfully led the 1950's battle for a car-free Washington Square Park, defeating Robert Moses' plan to carve a four-lane highway through it linking Fifth Avenue with West Broadway.
Hayes was also active in many other community issues. These include renovating Washington Square Park after it was closed to traffic, getting more playgrounds in the Greenwich Village area, opposing the NYU Bobst Library, and fighting large apartment buildings on Washington Square Park. Hayes was a dedicated record keeper, so the collection contains records of many of the organizations that she was involved with including the Washington Square Park Committee.
Her community involvement also included participating in political campaigns. Hayes was active in several campaigns of John Lindsay, who was a congressman and mayor of New York City. The political records she kept also pertain to other local politicians.
She also kept records pertaining to her time at WNYC and her involvement in the American Federation of Television and Radio Arts. Also included in this collection are some personal materials of Hayes.
The collection contains a wide variety of materials including correspondence, reports, press releases, statements and speeches, petitions, photographs, maps, flyers, posters, receipts and other financial documents, clippings, audio and videotape, political campaign materials, handwritten notes and drafts, publications, and personal ephemera.
Separated Material
Duplicate newspaper clippings have been separated. See Series XV.
Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Washington Square Park (New York, NY); City planning -- New York (State) -- New York.; Community foundations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York.; Traffic flow -- New York (State) -- New York.; Urban renewal -- Citizen participation.; Ballots.; Banners.; Circulars (fliers).; Clippings (information artifacts); Drafts (documents); Fliers (printed matter); Letters (correspondence); Maps.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Notes (documents); Petitions.; Photographs.; Posters.; Press releases.; Prints (visual works).; Reports.; Résumés (personnel records); Sound recordings.; Surveys.; Video recordings (physical artifacts); Community Planning Board No. 2 (New York, N.Y.); Greenwich Village Association (New York, N.Y.); New York University; Washington Square Association (New York, N.Y.); Washington Square Park Committee (New York, N.Y.); WNYC (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); Abrams, Charles, 1902-1970; Curran, Henry; Hayes, Shirley, 1921-2001; Koch, Ed, 1924-2013; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); Mitchell, MacNeil; Moses, Robert, 1888-1981; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962
- Series I. Washington Square Park Battle, 1952-1959
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains three sub-series. It contains a variety of material from the fight to close Washington Square Park to traffic and housing issues from various community organizations. Materials included are minutes, reports, financial documents, press releases, correspondence, speeches, petitions, and surveys.
  - Subseries I.A. Washington Square Park Committee
    This sub-series contains materials from the Washington Square Park Committee, a committee formed to discuss issues related to Washington Square Park. Hayes was a founding member of this committee and was chairperson. The types of materials included are minutes, reports, mailings, financial documents, and press releases.
    - General correspondence: Received by Shirley Hayes / Washington Square Park Committee, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence: Received by Shirley Hayes / Washington Square Park Committee, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence: Received by Shirley Hayes / Washington Square Park Committee, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General correspondence: Sent by Shirley Hayes / Washington Square Park Committee, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General correspondence: Sent by Shirley Hayes / Washington Square Park Committee, 1955-1657 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General correspondence: Sent by Shirley Hayes / Washington Square Park Committee, 1958-1959, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Other correspondents, 1956-1959, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Meeting minutes, 1952-1954, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Reports, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Financial documents, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Financial documents, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Financial documents, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Financial documents, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Financial forms, notes, and alienated envelopes, 1956, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Press releases and associated materials, 1953-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Press releases and associated materials, 1958-1959, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Traffic lssues in NYC and around the nation—Articles and notes, 1955-1959, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Traffic—Transportation consultant correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Traffic—Survey, 1958-1959, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Speeches and transcripts, 1952-1958, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Statements regarding Washington Square Park, 1952-1958, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Washington Square Park—Letter and speech drafts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Washington Square Park—Notes and fragments, 1958, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Meeting attendees lists, 1957-1958, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Neighborhood "Master Lists", 1957, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Lists of individuals and organizations (1 of 2), 1952-1958, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Lists of individuals and organizations (2 of 2), 1955-1958, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Mailings, 1952-1958, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Drafts, 1952-1959, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Returned mail used to update mailing lists, 1955, 1958, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Unsent mail, 1955, 1959, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Washington Square Park and Joint Emergency Committee—Letterhead, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Washington Square Park and Joint Emergency Committee—Envelopes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Subseries I.B. Community Campaigns and Support
    This sub-series contains letters sent and received from individuals and community organizations in support of closing the park to traffic. Also included are petitions to close the park to traffic.
    - Letters—Individuals and organizations, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Letters—Political candidates, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letters—Individuals, 1953-1954, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters—Schools, PTAs, Churches, 1953-1954, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Letters—Individuals, 1955, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Letters—Schools, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Letters—Schools and churches, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Citizens Union, 1954-1958, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Consents, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Petitions, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Tearoff campaign, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Tearoff campaign, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Postcard campaign, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Subseries I.C. Other Community Groups
    Sub-series three contains records of various other Greenwich Village area community groups in which Hayes was involved in. The types of materials included are correspondence, press releases, minutes, newsletters, posters, and clippings. This sub-series contains letters sent and received from individuals and community organizations in support of closing the park to traffic. Also included are petitions to close the park to traffic.
    - Joint Emergency Committee, 1958, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Greenwich Village Association, 1953-1959, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Washington Square Association, 1952-1956, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Various other community groups, 1953-1958, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series II. Washington Square Park Renovation Effort, 1958-1969
  In this series is material relating to renovating the park after it was closed to traffic. Hayes led the movement to renovate the park. The types of materials included are maps, surveys, correspondence, drafts, and clippings.
  - Campaign to renovate park, 1958-1966, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Washington Square Park renovation clippings, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series III. Greenwich Village Battles, 1960-1993
  Many other issues surrounding Washington Square Park and Greenwich Village area are included in this series, including removing the buses from the park and fighting the construction of New York University's library. The materials contained in the series are letters, statements, announcements, and newsletters.
  - Final removal of buses from Washington Square Park, 1960-1963, Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - NYU Library controversy, 1961-1966, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Other Village issues and involvement, 1960-1973, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - NYU attempt to close Washington Place, 1993, Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series IV. Greenwich Village / Washington Square Park—Histories, 1988
  This series contains a draft of a manuscript although it does not indicate who wrote it. The series also contains information on a history workshop Hayes spoke at. The types of materials are letters, flyers, speech notes, newsletters and a video.
  - Untitled manuscript, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Washington Square history workshop—Flyers and speech drafts, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Washington Square history workshop—Video, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Series V. Community Planning Board #2, 1952-1993
  This series contains the records of Community Planning Board #2. Hayes was a committee member and member of the Parks and Playground Committee, which was a part of Community Planning Board #2. Materials included are minutes, flyers, petitions, maps, correspondence, and reports. There is a gap in the records of the minutes from 1965 to 1974.
  - Meeting minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Meeting minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Meeting minutes, 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Meeting minutes, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Meeting minutes, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Meeting minutes, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Meeting minutes, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Meeting minutes, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Parks and Playground Committee, 1954-1955, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - P.A.L.—NYU Playground, 1952-1956, Undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 6th Avenue Playground, 1953-1954, Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - P.S. 3 Playground, 1954-1955, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Abingdon Square Park, 1959-1966, Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Various Planning Board activities, 1952-1993, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Traffic issues, 1966, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Original members, early minutes, and 25th anniversary celebration, 1951-1977, Undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Village real estate redevelopment, 1952-1959, Undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Village and park maps, 1952-1966, Undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Greenwich Village Association Housing Committee Findings, Report and Handbook, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Statistical Guide to Greenwich Village, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Greenwich Village: Statistical Trends and Observations, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Board of Estimate calendar, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Board of Estimate calendar, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Board of Estimate calendar, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Community Planning handbook, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Series VI. City Publications, 1952-1993
  The records contained in this series are city publications relating to living in New York City. Also included is one folder (Box 1, Folder 3) on regional planning.
  - City Planning News, 1967-1977 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Department of City Planning newsletters, 1968-1970 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Population Changes in New York City, Department of City Planning bulletin, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Comprehensive Redevelopment Plan for New York City, Leonard S. Gans Co., Inc., 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Eviction Regulations, 1957, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Statistical Guide for New York City, Dept. of Commerce and Industrial Development, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - People and Plans: Vest Pocket Housing—The First Step in New York's Model Cities Program, Housing Development Administration, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Brooklyn Progress—Annual Report, Office of President, Borough of Brooklyn, City of New York, 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Towards Effective Citizen Planning, Testimony by John E. Zuccotti, Chairman NYC Planning Commission before the State Charter Revision Commission for NYC, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Group Homes in New York City, Marge Benjamin and Louis Murray, Dept. of City Planning, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Greenwich Village Auto Free Zone—Draft, Department of City Planning, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Various City Planning newsletters, pamphlets, flyers, press releases, and other materials, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Various City Planning newsletters, pamphlets, flyers, press releases, and other materials, 1970-1976, Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Regional Planning brochures, 1967-1976, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Series VII. Political Campaigns, 1952-1969
  Hayes was involved in local politics and helped on several election campaigns. In this series are her records of her activities in the campaigns and information on local politics. The materials included are campaign materials, notes, press releases, newsletters, correspondence and clippings.
  - Local politics, 1952-1964, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Lists and election returns, 1965-1968, Undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Campaign 1964—John Lindsay, Congressional re-election, 1964, Undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Campaign 1965—John Lindsay, Mayoral election, 1964, Undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Campaign 1965—Entertainment: Correspondence, releases, block parties, Lindsay 'Hops', 1965, Undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Campaign 1965—Entertainment: Notes, lists, clippings, 1965, Undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Campaign 1965—Campaign literature, Lindsay and other candidates, 1965, Undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Mayoral primaries, 1969, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Mayoral campaign—Re-election releases, events, campaign literature, and contributions, 1969, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Mayoral campaign—Re-election correspondence, notes, clippings, staff list, voters directory, 1969, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Lindsay Re-election poster, Undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Series VIII. WNYC, American Federation of Television and Radio Arts (AFTRA) and Related Materials, 1960-1978
  Hayes starting working at WNYC in 1966 as an announcer. This series contains records from her time there and also from AFTRA. The materials included are program highlights, press releases, reports and annual convention material. Also included are some AFTRA publications.
  - WNYC, 1967-1978, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - AFTRA, 1960, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - AFTRA, 1979, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - AFTRA publications, 1977-1979, Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences nallots, 1964-1969, Undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Series IX. Other Organizations, Events, Activities and Issues of Interest to Shirley Hayes, 1951-1976
  Series nine contains information on other interests of Hayes, including education, children, libraries, and women's interests. The types of materials included are minutes, correspondence, newsletters, ballots, and clippings.
  - Citizens Committee on Children of NYC, Inc., 1951-1955, 1961, Undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Education—City and country Schools, including Community Affairs Committee and student publications, 1952-1961, Undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Education—Interschool Committee / Councils, 1949-1953, Undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Education—Public Education Association, 1953-1961, Undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Education in general, 1953-1966, Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Higher education, 1957-1967, Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Child rearing and juvenile delinquency—Newspaper clippings, 1956,1966, Undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Libraries, 1956, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Women's City Club of New York—Publications, 1956, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Waterfront issues: Minutes, reports, memos, press releases, and flyers, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Waterfront issues: Minutes, reports, memos, press releases, and flyers, 1968-1976, Undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Waterfront issues: Publications, 1966-1974 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence regarding "Shirley Hayes Circle"—Effort to have center of Washington Square Park named for Hayes, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - "Puerto Rico and Us" (pamphlet), [1953] (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Ideology and Co-Existence: Moral Re-Armament (booklet), 1959 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - This is the Truth!—Brotherhood's Committee's Reply to The Villager (announcement), 1960 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Greenwich Village Parade flyer, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Let the World Aid America—The Trade Expansion Act of 1962 (statement) (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - After Robert Moses, What?—An Exploration of New Ways of Governing Cities and Institutions (brochure), 1975 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - New York Landmarks (pamphlet), Undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Advertisement for Victor M. Villemain, Undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Castle Clinton restoration (description), Undated (Box 13, Folder 18)
- Series X. Personal Items, 1948-2001
  This series contains personal correspondence written to and from Hayes, resumes, clippings relating to personal interests, ephemera, and items her children copied to include. Most of the material included in folder six is available in other series in the collection.
  - Personal correspondence, 1952-1989, Undated (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1948-1974, Undated (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Ephemera—Children's school materials, flyers, receipts, pamphlets, ads, 1957-1965, Undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Résumés and associated materials, including obituary notes, 1967-1998, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Materials selected for résumés—Articles, clippings, drafts, 1952-1976, Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Surprise party—Washington Square Park Committee, 1959, Undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - "L'Affaire Gold Key"—Honor from The Villager (Hayes did not accept), 1959, Undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Shirley Hayes plaque materials—Washington Square Park, 2000-2001, Undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Copies of various items selected by Hayes' children, 1952-1998, Undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Series XI. Articles and Clippings, 1952-1980
  This series contains articles and clippings from newspapers and magazines relating to Washington Square Park and other interests of Hayes.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - The New Yorker—Washington Square Park (pp. 61-63), August 12, 1952 Issues (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings—"Attack by Courtney Campbell and Report of W.S.A.", 1952-1953 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Traffic—Clippings, 1952-1959, Undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - City Planning—Clippings, 1952-1960 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - City Planning—Clippings, 1961-1969, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings—West Broadway, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1957 Jan. - May (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1957 June - Dec. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958 Jan. - Mar. (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - The New Yorker—Washington Square Park (pp. 24-25), March 26, 1958 Issue (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958 Apr. - June (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958 July - Oct. (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958 Nov. - Dec. (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1959 Jan. - May (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1959 June - Nov. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings—Letters to the Editor, 1953-1959, Undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1960-1973 (Box 16, Folder 3)